<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-09-18T18:57:25+00:00</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Darren Sim</title><subtitle>Tech Lead, Developer, Speaker &amp; Author in New Zealand</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Notes on Original Thinkers</title><link href="/notes-on-original-thinkers/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Notes on Original Thinkers" /><published>2019-08-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-08-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/notes-on-original-thinkers</id><content type="html" xml:base="/notes-on-original-thinkers/">&lt;p&gt;These are notes which I’ve taken from the TED Talk &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fxbCHn6gE3U&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The surprising habits of original thinkers&lt;/strong&gt; by Adam Grant&lt;/a&gt;. This talk provides insights on how to be an original / creative / innovative thinker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;who-are-the-originals&quot;&gt;Who are the Originals&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Originals are non-conformist&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;People who not only have new ideas, but also take action and champion them&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;People who stand-up and speak-up&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;People who drive creativity and change in this world&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;characteristics-of-originals&quot;&gt;Characteristics of Originals&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;originals-are-late-to-the-party&quot;&gt;Originals are late to the party&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Procrastinators are rated more creative than pre-crastinators&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Procrastination give you time to think about original ideas&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Procrastination is only good when you have started first, then procrastinate, and and take time to think deeply about the topic&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Failure Rates for First Movers vs Improvers&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/the-surprising-habits-of-original-thinkers-first-movers.png&quot; alt=&quot;Failure Rates for First Movers vs Improvers&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;originals-feel-doubt-and-fear&quot;&gt;Originals feel doubt and fear&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/the-surprising-habits-of-original-thinkers-creative-process.png&quot; alt=&quot;Creative process for most people&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There are two types of doubt, self doubt (paralyzing) and idea doubt (energizing)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Key to being original is to avoid step 3 to step 4. Instead of saying “I’m crap”, you just say “all the ideas are crap” till you get the idea you are satisfied with&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Research shows that users of Firefox &amp;amp; Chrome are more likely to be successful; such users doubt the default and look for better options&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Original feels fear; but they are even more afraid to not try&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You are not going to be judged on your bad ideas&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If we want to be more original, we have to try more ideas. You have to have a lot of bad ideas in order to get a few good ones.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>sal</name></author><summary type="html">These are notes which I’ve taken from the TED Talk The surprising habits of original thinkers by Adam Grant. This talk provides insights on how to be an original / creative / innovative thinker.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/assets/images/posts/the-surprising-habits-of-original-thinkers-graph.png" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Tips for Running a Code Kata (Developer Dojo) at the Workplace</title><link href="/tips-for-running-a-code-kata-developer-dojo-at-the-workplace/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tips for Running a Code Kata (Developer Dojo) at the Workplace" /><published>2018-07-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-07-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/tips-for-running-a-code-kata-developer-dojo-at-the-workplace</id><content type="html" xml:base="/tips-for-running-a-code-kata-developer-dojo-at-the-workplace/">&lt;p&gt;A concept borrowed from the Japanese martial arts world, katas are exercises which help practitioners hone their skills through practice and repetition. Over the past decade, katas has been adopted as part of the wider Software Craftsmanship movement, seeing katas introduced as part of leading Software Development and Software Architecture courses around the world.
Organisations and software teams that embrace this practice has increasingly prioritised time for software practitioners to work on katas together, at a regular cadence. This provides a safe space for teams to &lt;strong&gt;experiment new practices&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;hone new skills&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;challenge assumptions&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;work with team members they do not usually interact with&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-happens-during-a-code-kata-session&quot;&gt;What happens during a Code Kata Session&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Code Katas usually last between 2 - 4 hours, and are conducted in spaces with minimal interruptions. While it is ideal to have these sessions in a meeting or conference room, team-spaces can work too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These sessions (code katas) are usually facilitated by someone with practical experience - for the practice/skill the group is trying to hone, and has done the kata more than once. During the course of the Kata, collaboration techniques such as pair-programming and mob-programming can also be introduced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is always useful to work on Katas that focus on just one (never more than three) practice, on a tool and language that team members are already familiar with. This minimizes context switching and reduces frustrations on toolchain setup. If familiarization of the tool and/or language is in question, it always pays to organize a hand-on lab session prior, to onboard (installation plus training) team members onto the tools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is highly valuable to conclude each Kata with a &lt;strong&gt;retrospective&lt;/strong&gt;. This gives team members the opportunity to &lt;strong&gt;recap what they have learnt&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;give feedback on how the Kata can be improved&lt;/strong&gt;, and most importantly, &lt;strong&gt;how they are plan to exercise these new skills in their work&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-happens-after-the-session&quot;&gt;What happens after the session?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the practice is something new to the team en-mass, it always helps to repeat the same Kata a couple more times to help team members get familiar with the practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To accelerate a team’s learning of the practice, it will also be useful to invite someone - who has substantial experience with the practice, to “mob” on a real world user story with the team. This person can be from the same organization, an external organization that the company has a trusted relationship with, a local community leader, or an external consultant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This helps the team:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;localize the practice to make it practical for the team,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;see that this new practice can actually work in real world production work, and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;opens up the opportunity for feedback on how the team might be able to improve their ways of working.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;frequently-asked-questions-faq&quot;&gt;Frequently Asked Questions (FAQ)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Duration - How long should a Kata be?&lt;/strong&gt;
Usually 120 minutes (2 hours) to 240 minutes (4 hours). 90 minutes might work in some situations where the team is already familiar with Katas and has some basic understanding (not necessarily practical) of the practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ideal Size - How many participants can a Code Kata session accommodate?&lt;/strong&gt;
4 to 10 participants per facilitator is the recommended ratio. It is generally discouraged for sessions to go beyond 40 participants as coordination becomes very difficult.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Setup - What resources are required to run a Code Kata session?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ideally a Conference / Meeting Room. Team area can work too.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Table and chairs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1 computer (laptop /pc) for every 2 persons&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Whiteboard&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Projection (Computer Projector / TV Screen)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sticky Notes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sharpies&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Printouts of the Katas (1 per participant)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Format - How does a Code Kata agenda or session plan look like?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Timeline&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Activity&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10 Minutes&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Introduction&lt;/strong&gt; Covering health &amp;amp; safely briefs, evacuation procedures, kata pre-requisites, and other general matters.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;20 Minutes&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Presentation on Concepts and Techniques&lt;/strong&gt; Introduction to concepts and practices that will be exercised within the Kata (e.g. TDD).&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;80 Minutes&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Interactive Kata Session&lt;/strong&gt; Participants are formed into groups (e.g. pairs) to work on the katas. Various collaboration techniques can be introduced, in addition to the kata. It is recommended to perform a pulse check once every 20 minutes - this is a good time to swap pairs.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10 Minutes&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Retrospect on Activity&lt;/strong&gt; Talk through with participants on what they have learnt from the session, what it might be improved and how might they apply how they learnt into their ways of working.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;</content><author><name>sal</name></author><summary type="html">A concept borrowed from the Japanese martial arts world, katas are exercises which help practitioners hone their skills through practice and repetition. Over the past decade, katas has been adopted as part of the wider Software Craftsmanship movement, seeing katas introduced as part of leading Software Development and Software Architecture courses around the world. Organisations and software teams that embrace this practice has increasingly prioritised time for software practitioners to work on katas together, at a regular cadence. This provides a safe space for teams to experiment new practices, hone new skills, challenge assumptions and work with team members they do not usually interact with.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/assets/images/posts/coding-dojo.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Introduction to Feature Toggles and Implementation Best Practices</title><link href="/introduction-to-feature-toggles-and-implementation-best-practices/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Introduction to Feature Toggles and Implementation Best Practices" /><published>2018-06-24T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-06-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/introduction-to-feature-toggles-and-implementation-best-practices</id><content type="html" xml:base="/introduction-to-feature-toggles-and-implementation-best-practices/">As software professionals, success is measured by our ability to improve our users’ lives.

Unlike other engineering fields which have been around for hundreds of years, the software engineering discipline has existed for barely a hundred years. As an industry, software development is still largely part-art, part-science.

With the ever evolving business and technological landscape, many of our past experiences serve merely as references. Adding to the unknowns, users seldom know what features they want, but they know what they don’t want. More often than not, it takes several attempts of trial-and-error before software teams become successful in delivering features that stick.

The ability to continuously deliver working software into the hands of customers, has served as a competitive advantage for leading tech companies like Amazon and Facebook. Not only did this capability allow engineering teams to deploy code into production in small chunks, quickly, and safely, it also shortened the feedback loop - allowing teams to learn fast and respond to changes quickly.

In the practice of Continuous Delivery (CD), it's important that the application is continuously integrated (CI), and deployable at all times. This can be challenging especially in situations where a feature spans multiple commits, and, an urgent fix needs to be released before the development of that feature is complete. This highlights the need for deployment and release to be decoupled.

When a feature is completed and deployed to production, teams also need a way to experiment safely, beta testing with a small group of users and being able to roll back quickly if an undesirable experience is observed.

Feature Toggles offers options to overcome to these challenges.

In this article, we will explore: &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;1) what feature toggles are&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2) how we can use them&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, before &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3) discussing best practices&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.
&lt;h3&gt;What are Feature Toggles?&lt;/h3&gt;
Feature Toggling is not a new concept and was a common practice more than 20 years ago, in the absence of reliable and easy-to-use concurrent versioning systems (CVS). In recent years, Feature Toggle experienced a resurgence with the popularisation of DevOps practices and mindsets within software development teams.

Also known as “Feature Flags”, “Config Flags”, “Flippers”, “Feature Bits” and “Conditional Feature”, Feature Toggling is a set of patterns that help teams deliver new functionally to users rapidly but safely, separating deployment from release, allowing teams to modify system behavior without changing code. Implemented by simply wrapping an if-statement around a code block that we are trying to isolate, the condition of this if-statement can be a simple boolean or complex decision trees with multiple paths.

The basic idea here is that we have a configuration system that allows the development team to toggle features on or off. When the application is executed, it will use these toggles to decide what features to display. The actual implementation will vary - ranging from a hard-coded configuration value within the application where changing the toggle configurations require a redeployment of the application, to reading toggle states from a text file, or a web service, allowing teams to modify toggle configurations at runtime.

Some of the benefits that Feature Toggles bring to the table include helping teams eliminate nasty merge conflicts, reduce deployment risks and achieving a shorter feedback loop. However, there’s always two side of a coin. Apart from introducing technical debt the moment we use Feature Toggles in our code, Feature Toggles also results in code being more fragile, harder to test, harder to maintain, and harder to support. Hence, Feature Toggles should always be short-lived, and used on a need-be basis rather than it being the silver-bullet to software development.

One of the most common misunderstandings of Feature Toggles is that it can double as a licensing and authorization service. This results in tight coupling of responsibility and should be avoided.
&lt;h3&gt;Types of Feature Toggles&lt;/h3&gt;
In his thought-leading article &lt;a href=&quot;https://martinfowler.com/articles/feature-toggles.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;“Feature Toggles (aka Feature Flags)”&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.thepete.net/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;Pete Hodgson&lt;/a&gt; extended &lt;a href=&quot;https://martinfowler.com/aboutMe.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;Martin Fowler&lt;/a&gt;’s original post “&lt;a href=&quot;https://martinfowler.com/bliki/FeatureToggle.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;FeatureToggle&lt;/a&gt;”, nicely categorizing Feature Toggles into FOUR categories:

&lt;strong&gt;Short-Lived Toggles&lt;/strong&gt;

&lt;table style=&quot;width: 100%;&quot;&gt;
   &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;width: 20%; background-color: #bbb; font-weight: bold;&quot;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;width: 40%; background-color: #bbb; font-weight: bold; text-align: center;&quot;&gt;Release Toggle&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;width: 40%; background-color: #bbb; font-weight: bold; text-align: center;&quot;&gt;Experimental Toggle&lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;/tr&gt;
   &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;background-color: #ddd; font-weight: bold; text-align: center;&quot;&gt;Dynamism&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot;&gt;Largely static, changing release toggle decision usually done in code; requiring redeployment.&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot;&gt;Highly dynamic; changes with each request&lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;/tr&gt;
   &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;background-color: #ddd; font-weight: bold; text-align: center;&quot;&gt;Longevity&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot;&gt;Transitionary by nature; should not stick around longer than 1 weeks.&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot;&gt;Long enough to generate statically significant results, usually kept around for hours to weeks.&lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;/tr&gt;
   &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;background-color: #ddd; font-weight: bold; text-align: center;&quot;&gt;Benefits&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot;&gt;Allows incomplete and untested code-paths to be deployed to production.&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot;&gt;Provides development team with means to make data-driven decisions.&lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;/tr&gt;
   &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;background-color: #ddd; font-weight: bold; text-align: center;&quot;&gt;Disadvantages&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot;&gt;Results in dead code that will not add value to anyone.&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot;&gt;Highly dynamic in nature, requiring a third-party services; a conscious technical debt.&lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;/tr&gt;
   &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;background-color: #ddd; font-weight: bold; text-align: center;&quot;&gt;Implementation&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot;&gt;By hardcoding the condition in the if-statement to false.&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot;&gt;Usually by means of an external feature toggle web service.&lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;/tr&gt;
   &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;background-color: #ddd; font-weight: bold; text-align: center;&quot;&gt;When to Use&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot;&gt;When developing code that is not ready for consumption and has a high risk of breaking the application.&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot;&gt;When performing multivariate testing (e.g. AB Testing)&lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;strong&gt;Long-Lived Toggles&lt;/strong&gt;

&lt;table style=&quot;width: 100%;&quot;&gt;
   &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;width: 20%; background-color: #bbb; font-weight: bold;&quot;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;width: 40%; background-color: #bbb; font-weight: bold; text-align: center;&quot;&gt;Operation Toggle&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;width: 40%; background-color: #bbb; font-weight: bold; text-align: center;&quot;&gt;Permission Toggle&lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;/tr&gt;
   &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;background-color: #ddd; font-weight: bold; text-align: center;&quot;&gt;Dynamism&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot;&gt;Relatively static; changes be done with runtime reconfiguration.&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot;&gt;Highly dynamic in nature; changes may happen between requests.&lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;/tr&gt;
   &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;background-color: #ddd; font-weight: bold; text-align: center;&quot;&gt;Longevity&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot;&gt;Usually from weeks to years.&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot;&gt;Usually spanning months to years.&lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;/tr&gt;
   &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;background-color: #ddd; font-weight: bold; text-align: center;&quot;&gt;Benefits&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot;&gt;Allows system operators to disable / degrade a low performing feature quickly without having to perform a redeployment of the code.&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot;&gt;Perform targeted experiments and learnings.&lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;/tr&gt;
   &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;background-color: #ddd; font-weight: bold; text-align: center;&quot;&gt;Disadvantages&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot;&gt;Tends to stick around forever; leading to increased system complexity.&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot;&gt;Tends to stick around forever; leading to increased system complexity.&lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;/tr&gt;
   &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;background-color: #ddd; font-weight: bold; text-align: center;&quot;&gt;Implementation&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot;&gt;By means of a config file on a CDN or other means of data cache services.&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot;&gt;Usually by means of an external feature toggle web service.&lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;/tr&gt;
   &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;background-color: #ddd; font-weight: bold; text-align: center;&quot;&gt;When to Use&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot;&gt;When rolling out a new feature with unclear performance impact.&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot;&gt;Used in cases of dog-fooding, alpha and beta programs.&lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

While this categorization is by no means all-encompassing, it serves as a good reference when making decisions on designing Feature Toggles implementations.
&lt;h3&gt;My Team’s Experience with Feature Toggles&lt;/h3&gt;
My team has been working with feature Toggles for the last 18 months and have gone from using an internally developed, maintained and hosted Feature Toggling service, to a commercial operated SaaS-based solution.

Our bread and butters as a team is to build and operate a management dashboard for accountants and book keepers. Through this dashboard, our users will be able to get a birds’ eye view of all their client’s accounting books (also known as “ledgers”) and categorize transactions (also known as “transaction coding”) where required. Data is fed to this management dashboard through a plethora of web services that are maintained by various teams within the organization.

The management dashboard comprises of a front-end shell that deals with everything that runs on the browser, as well as a backend service that acts as a data aggregation and caching service, used exclusively by the front-end.

In our team, we have adopted practices such as Continuous Integration (CI), Continuous Deployment (CD), Trunk-based Development and Test-Driven Development to help us deliver working software quickly and safely.

Given that we practice elephant carpaccio during story slicing and work mainly in a mob or as pairs, we found Release Toggles to be less useful. Instead, we adopted the Feature Branching approach when developing new features. With Feature Branching, we are able to make multiple commits while working on the feature, without generating excessive noise in GIT. As we squash our commits with links back to the original feature branch, GitHub allow us the ability to rid the feature branch, while still being able to look back at those micro-commits.

The two toggles that we used were &lt;strong&gt;Operations Toggles&lt;/strong&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;Permission Toggles&lt;/strong&gt;.

As a downstream service that depends on many other services for data, the ball is seldom in our courts. Each of these services that we depend on for data, is usually built and operated by different teams, and has varying performance thresholds.

Operation Toggles has been especially effective; offering us the capability to gracefully degrade or disable calls to these dependent services in the event that the business dashboard or any of it downstream services experience a traffic surge resulting in undesirable system performances and/or behaviors.

Given that this services doesn’t have to be highly dynamic, we developed a simple setup that required little to no maintenance. Backed by an AWS S3 bucket to store a static configuration and a CloudFront Distribution to deliver the configuration payload, this infrastructure cost us close to nothing to operate.

In order to better understand if features were developed and delivered in a way that actually increases the productivity and effectiveness of our users, we have also introduced beta programs to get early feedback before a feature is released to the entire user base.

Given that this service needs to be able to form toggle configurations dynamically based on a user’s profile, locality and many other factors, a highly dynamic service is required. Leading vendors that offers such services include FeatureAvailability.IO, Launch Darkly, and Split.IO. Given that these services usually offer very similar feature offerings and pricing, decisions usually boils down to product roadmaps, and quality of support. Flagr and Petri are two popular open source options that can be downloaded and self-hosted.

Commercially operated solutions typically charge based on a per-request model; hence implementing on stateless functions (e.g. AWS Lamda) can be costly given that caching of this state is not possible. Feature Toggle states are usually cached for up to a minute within an application to reduce the chattiness between the application and the Feature Toggle service.
&lt;h3&gt;Feature Toggle Best Practices&lt;/h3&gt;
Feature Toggling is a useful technique that helps team avoid painful merge conflicts, experiment and learn fast; however not without risks. Here are some of my lessons learnt and best practices:

&lt;strong&gt;Business Metric and Traffic Monitoring Dashboard&lt;/strong&gt;
A key benefit of Feature Toggling is the ability to perform experiments and learn from feedback, quickly and safely. Hence having a business metric dashboard is of high importance, allowing us to understand the business impact of a new feature. Consider an e-commerce system; if the introduction of a new feature results in massive decrease in sales, that is something that is probably a useful feedback that is worth looking into in greater detail.

&lt;strong&gt;Avoid Using Release Toggles&lt;/strong&gt;
As Martin Fowler has put it, while release toggles is a useful technique that is used by many teams, they should be used as a last option when putting new features into production. Instead, we should be adopting the practice of breaking features down more so that they can be safely introduced into the product. The benefit of doing so is synonymous with that of any strategy advocating small and frequent releases. Risks can be reduced and development teams can get early feedback that can be used to improve the feature.

&lt;strong&gt;Avoid Coupling Decision Point and Toggle Router&lt;/strong&gt;
Decision point is defined as the location in the code that calls the toggle router, while the Toggle router contains the logic to check if a certain decision point is active by reading toggling configurations to detect features, or simply detect an Toggle Context.
&lt;pre&gt;if(User == “john@doe.com” &amp;amp;&amp;amp; Weather == “Sunny”){
      DoSomething();
}&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;if(User.Segment == “Beta”){
      DoSomething();
}&lt;/pre&gt;
The two examples above exemplifies patterns we want to avoid, as they tightly couple toggles decisions into the application logic.
&lt;pre&gt;if(FeatureSwitchSvc.IsPsychicEnabled){
      DoSomething();
}&lt;/pre&gt;
What we want instead, is to de-couple decision points from decision logic by introducing a decision object that implements that logic. In this way, the strategy-pattern can be applied, encapsulating routing conditions to the routing layer. Thus a change in feature grouping will not break the code.

&lt;strong&gt;Avoid Nesting Feature Toggles&lt;/strong&gt;
If nesting if-statements increases the cyclomatic complexity; nesting Feature Toggles increases that by many folds.

&lt;strong&gt;Dashboard with Feature Toggles Longevity&lt;/strong&gt;
Like branches, long-lived feature toggles should be avoided as it adds significant complexity to the application and causes the code-base to be brittle over time. While it is easy to visualize how many stale branches you have in Github, long-lived feature toggles are less obvious and runs the risks of snuggling in forever. Hence a physical or digital dashboard in the team area that keeps track of the longevity of each Feature Toggle is always a good practice.

&lt;strong&gt;Always Check for Security&lt;/strong&gt;
One of the common misconceptions is that if you hide a feature behind a feature flag, it is not accessible and hence we do not have to worry about security. This is untrue and a dangerous mindset to have in software development; a phenomenal known as &quot;the security sandwich&quot;. Consider a feature toggle implemented on the front-end. What is stopping a malicious user from manually setting that flag to true in the console? Security as an afterthought is always recipe for trouble.

&lt;strong&gt;Automated Tests Should Exercise Both Toggle On and Off States&lt;/strong&gt;
If TDD is practiced in the team, it is always a good habit to practice red-green-refactor. When implementing feature toggles, it is always important that automated tests exercise flows with the switch turned on, and off, to avoid regressions. While this is not a silver bullet, it helps radiate obvious regressions. The added complexity in testing introduced by feature toggles warrants reviewing existing test strategies; constant and effective communication between between members of the development team is also important.


&lt;pre&gt;This article was first published in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20180624072619/https://pragprog.com/news/node-js-8-the-right-way-practical-server-side-javascript-that-scales-in-print-january-pragpub&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;Jan 2018 issue&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href=&quot;https://theprosegarden.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;Pragmatic Publications Magazine&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/pre&gt;</content><author><name>sal</name></author><category term="featured" /><summary type="html">As software professionals, success is measured by our ability to improve our users’ lives.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/assets/images/posts/feature-toggle.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Dreyfus Learning Model</title><link href="/the-dreyfus-learning-model/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Dreyfus Learning Model" /><published>2018-06-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-06-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/the-dreyfus-learning-model</id><content type="html" xml:base="/the-dreyfus-learning-model/">&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;strong&gt;Novice&lt;/strong&gt; – at this stage a person doesn’t really know how to be successful at what they are doing, they don’t want the big picture, but instead want unambiguous rules that will allow them to successfully accomplish their tasks. They need quick successes and will be confused when anything out of the ordinary happens.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;strong&gt;Advanced Beginner&lt;/strong&gt; –  want to find the information they need quickly, they have some context regarding what they are doing but still not really interested in the big picture. They can use the skill at a more competent level than a novice but will still have trouble when things go wrong.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;strong&gt;Competent&lt;/strong&gt; – have the ability to see the big picture and how it would affect the outcomes. They can deal with problems when something unexpected occurs they are able to draw on their experience when necessary. However their ability to reflect on what they do is still somewhat limited.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;strong&gt;Proficient&lt;/strong&gt; – need the big picture and will not function well without it. They can reflect on how well they are doing and draw upon their experience to improve. Can draw relevant information from the experience of others rather than taking it in as a whole.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	&lt;strong&gt;Expert&lt;/strong&gt; – no longer require rules and guidelines to function, will intuitively know what to do in a given situation. They will also constantly seek to find better ways of doing things.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Source&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
 	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://animationresources.org/dreyfus-model&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;https://animationresources.org/dreyfus-model&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
 	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.skorks.com/2009/08/building-software-development-expertise-using-the-dreyfus-model/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;https://www.skorks.com/2009/08/building-software-development-expertise-using-the-dreyfus-model/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>sal</name></author><summary type="html">Novice – at this stage a person doesn’t really know how to be successful at what they are doing, they don’t want the big picture, but instead want unambiguous rules that will allow them to successfully accomplish their tasks. They need quick successes and will be confused when anything out of the ordinary happens. Advanced Beginner – want to find the information they need quickly, they have some context regarding what they are doing but still not really interested in the big picture. They can use the skill at a more competent level than a novice but will still have trouble when things go wrong. Competent – have the ability to see the big picture and how it would affect the outcomes. They can deal with problems when something unexpected occurs they are able to draw on their experience when necessary. However their ability to reflect on what they do is still somewhat limited. Proficient – need the big picture and will not function well without it. They can reflect on how well they are doing and draw upon their experience to improve. Can draw relevant information from the experience of others rather than taking it in as a whole. Expert – no longer require rules and guidelines to function, will intuitively know what to do in a given situation. They will also constantly seek to find better ways of doing things.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/assets/images/posts/dryfus-learning-model.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Enabling Detailed Monitoring on PostgreSQL RDS running on Amazon Web Services (AWS)</title><link href="/enabling-detailed-monitoring-postgresql-aws-rds-amazon-web-services/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Enabling Detailed Monitoring on PostgreSQL RDS running on Amazon Web Services (AWS)" /><published>2017-12-08T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-12-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/enabling-detailed-monitoring-postgresql-aws-rds-amazon-web-services</id><content type="html" xml:base="/enabling-detailed-monitoring-postgresql-aws-rds-amazon-web-services/">In micro-service implementations where servers are treated as disposable kettles rather than pets, the data-store (usually an RDS insurance on AWS) becomes ever more important; it's the single source of truth for the application.

While this is no longer considered the best practice, the following architecture, was at one time one of the more popular patterns.

&lt;img class=&quot;alignnone wp-image-107 size-large&quot; src=&quot;http://darrensim.io/wp-content/uploads/2017/10/AWS-Application-Architecture-1024x622.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;1024&quot; height=&quot;622&quot; /&gt;

Unfortunately, as teams do not usually give a lot of love to their infrastructure post initial setup, this setup is still pretty common.

&lt;h3&gt;Importance of Monitoring the RDS&lt;/h3&gt;

Given that a failure of the RDS is the most costly failure in such a setup, system operators (in teams that subscribe to the &quot;you build it, you run it&quot; mindset, this happens to be the Dev team) need to be preempted way ahead of time if there's a potential bottleneck forming, or a resource spike (e.g. CPU) that has the potential to bring the RDS to a crawl, rendering it unavailable.

In the event that a potential bottleneck or resource spike do occur, operators need to be able to have the right information on hand to quickly diagnose the issue and shutdown a bad node making calls to the RDS.

Out of the box, AWS provides the following metrics that are useful for general system health monitoring; enabling enhanced monitoring will offer operators the ability to monitor heuristically and perform diagnostics.

&lt;h3&gt;RDS Basic Monitoring Capabilities&lt;/h3&gt;

Basic monitoring comes by default with all RDS installations on AWS; the RDS sends metrics to CloudWatch for each active database instance every minute.

&lt;strong&gt;Metrics Available&lt;/strong&gt;
There are 24 metrics that are tracked in the Amazon RDS Metrics. These include:

[table id=6 /]

Read more on &lt;a href=&quot;http://docs.aws.amazon.com/AmazonCloudWatch/latest/monitoring/rds-metricscollected.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;http://docs.aws.amazon.com/AmazonCloudWatch/latest/monitoring/rds-metricscollected.html&lt;/a&gt;.

Of these, the FOUR metrics which I strongly recommend wiring up CloudWatch alarms to are &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;CPUUtilization&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DatabaseConnections&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;FreeableMemory&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;FreeStorageSpace&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.

&lt;h3&gt;Case for Detailed Monitoring&lt;/h3&gt;

One of the key difference between default CloudWatch monitoring, and Enhanced monitoring for RDS is, CloudWatch gathers metrics about CPU utilization &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;from the hypervisor&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; for a DB instance, while Enhanced Monitoring gathers its metrics &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;from an agent on the instance&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.

On top of receiving faster feedback &lt;em&gt;(1 second granularity)&lt;/em&gt; through having an agent on the instance, having an agent on the instance also brings about enhanced monitoring, that allows operators to see how different processes or threads on a DB instance use the CPU.

This is especially useful when operators want to find out which clients (e.g. EC2) are accessing the RDS, and how much CPU and memory utilization each of these clients is generating on the RDS.

&lt;strong&gt;Example Log Entry&lt;/strong&gt;

&lt;pre class=&quot;lang:default decode:true&quot; title=&quot;Example CloudWatch JSON Log&quot;&gt;{
    &quot;engine&quot;: &quot;POSTGRES&quot;,
    &quot;instanceID&quot;: &quot;INSTANCE_ID&quot;,
    &quot;instanceResourceID&quot;: &quot;db-RESOURCE_ID&quot;,
    &quot;timestamp&quot;: &quot;2017-10-30T11:17:55Z&quot;,
    &quot;version&quot;: 1,
    &quot;uptime&quot;: &quot;1 days, 20:17:10&quot;,
    &quot;numVCPUs&quot;: 8,
    &quot;cpuUtilization&quot;: {
        &quot;guest&quot;: 0,
        &quot;irq&quot;: 0.01,
        &quot;system&quot;: 0.26,
        &quot;wait&quot;: 0.26,
        &quot;idle&quot;: 94.31,
        &quot;user&quot;: 0.28,
        &quot;total&quot;: 5.68,
        &quot;steal&quot;: 0.01,
        &quot;nice&quot;: 4.86
    },
    &quot;loadAverageMinute&quot;: {
        &quot;fifteen&quot;: 0.51,
        &quot;five&quot;: 0.57,
        &quot;one&quot;: 0.62
    },
    &quot;memory&quot;: {
        &quot;writeback&quot;: 288,
        &quot;hugePagesFree&quot;: 0,
        &quot;hugePagesRsvd&quot;: 0,
        &quot;hugePagesSurp&quot;: 0,
        &quot;cached&quot;: 4805564,
        &quot;hugePagesSize&quot;: 2048,
        &quot;free&quot;: 26788288,
        &quot;hugePagesTotal&quot;: 0,
        &quot;inactive&quot;: 549000,
        &quot;pageTables&quot;: 30344,
        &quot;dirty&quot;: 100,
        &quot;mapped&quot;: 854956,
        &quot;active&quot;: 5059444,
        &quot;total&quot;: 32952096,
        &quot;slab&quot;: 249920,
        &quot;buffers&quot;: 303744
    },
    &quot;tasks&quot;: {
        &quot;sleeping&quot;: 239,
        &quot;zombie&quot;: 0,
        &quot;running&quot;: 2,
        &quot;stopped&quot;: 0,
        &quot;total&quot;: 241,
        &quot;blocked&quot;: 0
    },
    &quot;swap&quot;: {
        &quot;cached&quot;: 0,
        &quot;total&quot;: 16383996,
        &quot;free&quot;: 16383996
    },
    &quot;network&quot;: [
        {
            &quot;interface&quot;: &quot;eth0&quot;,
            &quot;rx&quot;: 150548.8,
            &quot;tx&quot;: 376372.3
        }
    ],
    &quot;diskIO&quot;: [
        {
            &quot;writeKbPS&quot;: 89.6,
            &quot;readIOsPS&quot;: 0,
            &quot;await&quot;: 2.1,
            &quot;readKbPS&quot;: 0,
            &quot;rrqmPS&quot;: 0,
            &quot;util&quot;: 1.96,
            &quot;avgQueueLen&quot;: 0.26,
            &quot;tps&quot;: 12.6,
            &quot;readKb&quot;: 0,
            &quot;device&quot;: &quot;rdsdev&quot;,
            &quot;writeKb&quot;: 896,
            &quot;avgReqSz&quot;: 7.11,
            &quot;wrqmPS&quot;: 0,
            &quot;writeIOsPS&quot;: 12.6
        }
    ],
    &quot;fileSys&quot;: [
        {
            &quot;used&quot;: 1530088,
            &quot;name&quot;: &quot;rdsfilesys&quot;,
            &quot;usedFiles&quot;: 1788,
            &quot;usedFilePercent&quot;: 0.03,
            &quot;maxFiles&quot;: 6553600,
            &quot;mountPoint&quot;: &quot;/rdsdbdata&quot;,
            &quot;total&quot;: 103053476,
            &quot;usedPercent&quot;: 1.48
        }
    ],
    &quot;processList&quot;: [
        {
            &quot;vss&quot;: 1234567,
            &quot;name&quot;: &quot;postgres: user_name service_running 127.0.0.1 idle&quot;,
            &quot;tgid&quot;: 4322,
            &quot;vmlimit&quot;: 21222222,
            &quot;parentID&quot;: 1234,
            &quot;memoryUsedPc&quot;: 0.69,
            &quot;cpuUsedPc&quot;: 0.09,
            &quot;id&quot;: 4321,
            &quot;rss&quot;: 226424
        }
    ]
}&lt;/pre&gt;

Details on metrics available can be found on &lt;a href=&quot;http://docs.aws.amazon.com/AmazonRDS/latest/UserGuide/USER_Monitoring.OS.html?shortFooter=true#USER_Monitoring.OS.CloudWatchLogs&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;http://docs.aws.amazon.com/AmazonRDS/latest/UserGuide/USER_Monitoring.OS.html?shortFooter=true#USER_Monitoring.OS.CloudWatchLogs&lt;/a&gt;.

As of 2017, detailed monitoring is available for all DB instance classes (except for &lt;code&gt;db.t1.micro&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;db.m1.small&lt;/code&gt;), for the following database engines:

&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Amazon Aurora&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;MariaDB&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Microsoft SQL Server&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;MySQL version 5.5 or later&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Oracle&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;PostgreSQL&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Enabling Enhanced Monitoring on AWS RDS&lt;/h3&gt;

Enabling enhanced monitoring on an AWS RDS instance is really easy. This can be done by toggling the &quot;Enable Enhanced Monitoring&quot; setting on the AWS Management Console to &quot;Yes&quot;.

To do this:

&lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Login to the AWS Management Console&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Select RDS&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Click on DB Instances&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Select the specific instance&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Click on Instance Actions&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Select Modify&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;img class=&quot;alignnone size-full wp-image-105&quot; src=&quot;http://darrensim.io/wp-content/uploads/2017/10/RDS-Enhanced-Monitoring-Configuration.png&quot; alt=&quot;RDS Enhanced Monitoring Configuration on AWS Management Console&quot; width=&quot;540&quot; height=&quot;146&quot; /&gt;

Within the configuration panel, you will also be able to 1) &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;enable enhanced monitoring&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, 2) &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;select monitoring role&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, and 3) &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;select the granularity&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; of the monitoring (in units of 1, 5, 10, 15, 30, 60 seconds).

&lt;strong&gt;Is Maintenance Window Required?&lt;/strong&gt;

As this does not require a RDS reboot, the Maintenance Window is not required.

&lt;h3&gt;Cost Impact&lt;/h3&gt;

The cost of enabling enhanced monitoring depends on the amount of logs that are written to CloudWatch. The general rule of thumb is the greater the granularity, the more the logs generated, which in turn, results in an increased cost.

AWS CloudWatch offers 5 GB a month for free; there after it is chargeable. Costing structure of AWS CloudWatch can be found on &lt;a href=&quot;https://aws.amazon.com/cloudwatch/pricing/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;https://aws.amazon.com/cloudwatch/pricing/&lt;/a&gt;. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://calculator.s3.amazonaws.com/index.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;AWS cost calculator&lt;/a&gt; is another useful tool for cost estimations on AWS in general.

&lt;h3&gt;Accessing Logs&lt;/h3&gt;

Detailed logs generated from enhanced monitoring are stored as JSON format in CloudWatch, accessible via &lt;code&gt;CloudWatch &amp;gt; Log Groups &amp;gt; RDSOSMetrics &amp;gt; [Resource ID]&lt;/code&gt;.

&lt;h3&gt;Useful PostgreSQL Queries&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;strong&gt;Total connections made to the PostgreSQL instance&lt;/strong&gt;

&lt;pre class=&quot;lang:pgsql decode:true&quot; title=&quot;Total Connection made to the instances.&quot;&gt;SELECT client_addr, application_name, usename, datname, Count(1)
FROM   pg_stat_activity
GROUP  BY 1, 2, 3, 4
ORDER  BY 5 DESC;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;strong&gt;Only active connections on the PostgreSQL Instance&lt;/strong&gt;

&lt;pre class=&quot;lang:pgsql decode:true &quot; title=&quot;Only the active connection&quot;&gt;SELECT client_addr, application_name, usename, datname, Count(1)
FROM   pg_stat_activity
WHERE  state &amp;lt;&amp;gt; 'idle'
GROUP  BY 1, 2, 3, 4
ORDER  BY 5 DESC;&lt;/pre&gt;

&amp;nbsp;</content><author><name>sal</name></author><summary type="html">In micro-service implementations where servers are treated as disposable kettles rather than pets, the data-store (usually an RDS insurance on AWS) becomes ever more important; it's the single source of truth for the application.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/assets/images/posts/aws-rds-postresql.png" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Security Vulnerability and Browser Performance Impact of target=”_blank”</title><link href="/security-vulnerability-and-browser-performance-impact-of-target_blank/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Security Vulnerability and Browser Performance Impact of target=&amp;#8221;_blank&amp;#8221;" /><published>2017-11-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-11-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/security-vulnerability-and-browser-performance-impact-of-target_blank</id><content type="html" xml:base="/security-vulnerability-and-browser-performance-impact-of-target_blank/">The anchor tag &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.w3.org/MarkUp/1995-archive/Elements/A.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt; has been around in the &lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.w3.org/MarkUp/1995-archive/Elements/A.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;HTML standards&lt;/a&gt; for over 20 years, and has been the defecto standard for implementing in-page navigations, as well as navigations beyond the page. This has changed in recent years, with the popularity of javascript and single-page applications (SPAs); where page navigations are handled within onClick events of page elements instead.

Nonetheless, many of the concepts remain the same, and are handled by the browsers in almost the same way. The following code will give you the same behavior on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.techopedia.com/definition/31094/evergreen-browser&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;evergreen browsers&lt;/a&gt;.

&lt;strong&gt;HTML&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;a href=&quot;http://www.google.com&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&amp;gt;open me&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;

&lt;strong&gt;JavaScript&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;code&gt;window.open(&quot;http://www.google.com&quot;, &quot;_blank&quot;);&lt;/code&gt;

### Opening Links in New Browser Tabs

Navigation is one of the most important aspects of any modern web page or web application. Links can be largely categorized into two categories: **part of the user flow**, and **not part of the user flow**.

Links not considered as part of the user flow are generally considered a distraction; we often apply the `target=&quot;_blank&quot;` treatments to these links to open them in a separate browser window or browser tab. The `target=&quot;_blank&quot;` treatment is also the defecto standard for any outbound links to an external website.

While many would expect that opening an external link in a separate browser window / tab disassociates the external link from the host page, this is **not the case**.

When a browser window (or tab) is opened from another window using the JavaScript window.open function, or from a link with its target attribute set (e.g. `&lt;a href=&quot;site.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;`), it maintains a reference to that first window via the `window.opener` property in the page model.&lt;/a&gt;

### The Vulnerability

With a reference to the page that opens it, the _**newly opened page**_ (in a new window / tab) now has full control over the _**opening page**_'s window object. What this means is the _**newly opened page**_ can go as far as to change the location of the _**opening page**_.

While this might look relatively harmless, consider a scenario of a very popular online forum, where the newly opened page redirects users to a phishing page, asking for login credentials or other sensitive information.

![image-25](http://darrensim.io/wp-content/uploads/2017/11/target-blank-vulnerability-example-flow-1024x300.png)

I've created a [_**sample scenario**_](https://s3-ap-southeast-1.amazonaws.com/darrensimio-files/target-blank-vulnerability-example/homepage.html) available accessible via [https://s3-ap-southeast-1.amazonaws.com/darrensimio-files/target-blank-vulnerability-example/homepage.html](https://s3-ap-southeast-1.amazonaws.com/darrensimio-files/target-blank-vulnerability-example/homepage.html).

Following is the malicious code that will navigate the _**opening page**_ to a phishing page.

**The Malicious JavaScript Code**
[crayon-5ab92cc094b40192555268/]

### Resolving the Vulnerability

Fortunately, resolving this vulnerability is pretty straight forward.

In order to restrict access to the opening page from the newly opened page, all we need to do is to add the `rel=&quot;noopener&quot;` attribute to any link that has `target=&quot;_blank&quot;` on the opening page; this will work with the latest releases of Firefox, Chrome, Safari, and Opera. ([Click here](https://caniuse.com/#feat=rel-noopener) for list of browser supporting `rel=noopener`)

Alternatively, for older browsers, `rel=&quot;noreferrer&quot;` which also disables the Referrer HTTP header, can be used.

Following are the two implementations; one in html and the other in JavaScript.

**HTML**
[crayon-5ab92cc094b4e184317379/]
**JavaScript**
[crayon-5ab92cc094b56089495190/]

### Performance Impacts

While most modern browsers supports multi-process and multi-threading, parsing, style calculation, layout, painting and non-worker JavaScript happens in the same thread commonly known as the &quot;main&quot; thread. Each browser tab runs on its own &quot;main&quot; thread, preventing a resource hungry site running on a tab from bringing down the entire browser with it.

However, given that cross-window access provided via `window.opener` is synchronous, windows launched through `target=&quot;_blank&quot;` end up in the same process &amp;amp; thread. This applies to iframes and windows opened via `window.open` as well.

![image-24](http://darrensim.io/wp-content/uploads/2017/11/target-blank-page-freeze-example-flow-1024x300.png)

What this means is if the **newly opened page** is a resource hungry and slow performing site, it will result in performance degradation of the **opening page** (rendering the **opening page** inaccessible), and vice-versa. The introduction of new &quot;[throttling policy](https://developers.google.com/web/updates/2017/03/background_tabs)&quot; since [Chrome 57](https://developers.google.com/web/updates/2017/03/background_tabs) can add interesting complexities to this.

In the [sample scenario](https://s3-ap-southeast-1.amazonaws.com/darrensimio-files/target-blank-vulnerability-example/homepage.html) accessible via [https://s3-ap-southeast-1.amazonaws.com/darrensimio-files/target-blank-vulnerability-example/homepage.html](https://s3-ap-southeast-1.amazonaws.com/darrensimio-files/target-blank-vulnerability-example/homepage.html), we will observe that when we navigate to a low performing page, it causes the **opening page** to be unresponsive. Clicking, scrolling, or selecting text becomes no longer possible on the **opening page**.

This is all that the slow performing page is doing; running a while loop for 2 minutes.
[crayon-5ab92cc094b5b416152246/]

### Resolving Performance Impacts

Like the above example from _**resolving the vulnerability**_, `rel=&quot;noopener&quot;` prevents `window.opener`, so there's no cross-window access. Like the above example from resolving the vulnerability, `rel=&quot;noopener&quot;` prevents `window.opener`, so there's no cross-window access.

Unfortunately the JavaScript example did not work in my experiments with Chrome 61; it seems like chrome only disassociates the thread when `rel=&quot;noopener&quot;` is implemented.

What this means is that we will now need to use the window features options in the JavaScript `window.open()` function instead. While it worked, this was not an ideal implementation for me as using window features results in the **newly opened page** to be opened in a new browser window rather than a new tab.

(**Note:** Chrome will open the new window in a new tab if the window is set to full screen on the Mac; but will open in a new window if it is not in full screen mode.)

Following are the two implementations; one in html and the other in JavaScript.

**HTML**
[crayon-5ab92cc094b5e484295992/]
**JavaScript**
[crayon-5ab92cc094b65241329680/]

### Cross Browser Support

&lt;a href=&quot;https://caniuse.com/#search=noopener&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;aligncenter&quot; src=&quot;https://darrensim.io/wp-content/uploads/2017/11/can-i-use-no-opener-1024x389.png&quot; alt=&quot;Can I Use Noopener Tag in Browsers&quot; width=&quot;1024&quot; height=&quot;389&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

The screen capture above (extracted from [caniuse.com](https://caniuse.com/#search=noopener)), offers a nice summary of browsers that supports the `noopener` attribute. While this attribute is supported by most major evergreen browsers, it is intriguing to learn that this is not yet supported in the latest versions of Microsoft Edge.

The good news is this is not a call for concern at this point, as cross-window communication is pretty broken in Microsoft Edge. When Microsoft Edge moved to Universal Windows Platform (UWP), many cross-window communication that used to work in Win32 broke due to marshaling issues. This resulted in browser windows / tabs being forcibly isolated from each other, hence, we will not suffer from the shared main thread issue in this case.

When browsers eventually adds support for the [CSP](https://w3c.github.io/webappsec-csp/#directive-disown-opener) `disown-opener` [directive](https://w3c.github.io/webappsec-csp/#directive-disown-opener), youll be able to just use it as a meta tag in the `head` of your HTML page, or as an HTTP header. Either way the effect is to set `window.opener` to `null` for any new windows / tabs that get created from the document which includes that CSP directive.

**Meta Tag**
[crayon-5ab92cc094b69614010653/]
**HTTP Header**
[crayon-5ab92cc094b6b222696250/]

### Additional Readings

* Source code of the [sample scenarios](https://s3-ap-southeast-1.amazonaws.com/darrensimio-files/target-blank-vulnerability-example/homepage.html) used in this article can be found on [https://github.com/darrensimsg/target-blank-vulnerability-example](https://github.com/darrensimsg/target-blank-vulnerability-example).
* [https://jakearchibald.com/2016/performance-benefits-of-rel-noopener/](https://jakearchibald.com/2016/performance-benefits-of-rel-noopener/)
* [https://w3c.github.io/webappsec-csp/#directive-disown-opener](https://w3c.github.io/webappsec-csp/#directive-disown-opener)
* [https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/API/Window/open](https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/API/Window/open)</content><author><name>sal</name></author><summary type="html">The anchor tag has been around in the HTML standards for over 20 years, and has been the defecto standard for implementing in-page navigations, as well as navigations beyond the page. This has changed in recent years, with the popularity of javascript and single-page applications (SPAs); where page navigations are handled within onClick events of page elements instead.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/assets/images/posts/browser-security.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Setting up a Basic .NET Core Developer Environment with VSCode, xUnit and Moq on macOS</title><link href="/setting-up-a-basic-net-core-developer-environment-with-vscode-nunit-and-moq-on-macos/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Setting up a Basic .NET Core Developer Environment with VSCode, xUnit and Moq on macOS" /><published>2017-10-19T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-10-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/setting-up-a-basic-net-core-developer-environment-with-vscode-nunit-and-moq-on-macos</id><content type="html" xml:base="/setting-up-a-basic-net-core-developer-environment-with-vscode-nunit-and-moq-on-macos/">I've recently been kept awake late into the wee hours; working on really interesting code challenges on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.codewars.com/users/darrensimsg/&quot;&gt;Code Wars&lt;/a&gt;. While the problems are really fun to solve, one of the pains I found was to code on the web editor, which lacks the usual code editor features that I am comfortable with. Reluctant to load up the battery-draining Windows Virtual Machine just for this, I thought &quot;&lt;em&gt;Why not let me just create a simple boiler plate project in .NET Core that supports xUnit, which I can readily work on using VSCode on my macOS?&lt;/em&gt;&quot;
&lt;h3&gt;Language &amp; Frameworks&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;What is .NET Core?&lt;/strong&gt;

.NET Core is the cross-platform version of .NET Framework (at the layer of the Base Class Libraries) that is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.microsoft.com/net/core/support/&quot;&gt;officially supported&lt;/a&gt; my Microsoft, running on Windows, macOS, and Linux. Languages supported includes C#, Visual Basic and F#.

.NET Core is made up of FOUR primary components:
&lt;ul&gt;
 	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/dotnet/coreclr&quot;&gt;.NET Core Runtime&lt;/a&gt; (also known as CoreCLR)&lt;/li&gt;
 	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/dotnet/corefx&quot;&gt;Framework libraries&lt;/a&gt; (also known as CoreFX)&lt;/li&gt;
 	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/dotnet/cli&quot;&gt;SDK tools&lt;/a&gt; (made up of the Cli and Roslyn language compiler)&lt;/li&gt;
 	&lt;li&gt;App Host, which is used to launch .NET Core Apps&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;em&gt;(I will eventually be doing a couple of deep dive post on .NET Core in the near future)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is the current version?&lt;/strong&gt;

The current version of &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;.NET Core is version 2.0&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, which was shipped on August 14, 2017. The next version of the framework &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;.NET Core 2.1&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; is expected to ship in the first quarter of 2018.

The easiest way to find out what version of .NET Core you have installed is to enter this command into your terminal &lt;code&gt;dotnet --version&lt;/code&gt;. If terminal responds with something like &lt;code&gt;command not found: dotnet&lt;/code&gt;, that probably means you do not have .NET Core installed, or it's PATH has not been setup.

&lt;strong&gt;Installing .NET Core 2.x on macOS&lt;/strong&gt;

In order to install .NET Core 2.x on macOS, you need to be on macOS 10.12 &quot;Sierra&quot; or later versions. The best way to install .NET Core 2.x is to use the installer that's available for free, via &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.microsoft.com/net/core#macos&quot;&gt;https://www.microsoft.com/net/core#macos&lt;/a&gt;.

The installer will install the latest stable version of .NET Core SDK along with the tools, setting up the necessary PATH, that makes it easy for you to simply run the &lt;code&gt;dotnet&lt;/code&gt; command from the console.
&lt;h3&gt;Visual Studio Code&lt;/h3&gt;
Many who have worked with Visual Studio would be left with the impression that anything Visual Studio will be &quot;bloated&quot; and &quot;slow&quot;. Like many, I was hesitant to even install Visual Studio Code (also known as VSCode, a free and open sourced code editor by Microsoft) initially, passing it off as a glorified notepad app.

I eventually took the plunge; I've not had any regrets since! VS Code is amazingly lightweight, fast and powerful.

Based on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://electron.atom.io/&quot;&gt;electron framework&lt;/a&gt;, VS Code is in essence, a Node.js app, powered by a large repository of largely community contributed &lt;a href=&quot;https://marketplace.visualstudio.com/VSCode&quot;&gt;add-ons&lt;/a&gt; (called extensions). Based the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/Microsoft/monaco-editor&quot;&gt;monaco editor&lt;/a&gt; (an open source browser based code editor by Microsoft), VSCode comes with IntelliSense, git support, and debugging built-in.

VSCode is available for free, and runs on Windows, Linux and macOS.

&lt;strong&gt;Installing VS Code on macOS&lt;/strong&gt;

The two most popular ways of installing VSCode on the macOS are via &lt;code&gt;brew cask install visual-studio-code&lt;/code&gt;, or &lt;a href=&quot;https://code.visualstudio.com/&quot;&gt;simply downloading the executable&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;h3&gt;Creating a Basic C# Project with Unit Test&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Create a new .net console project&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;code&gt;dotnet new console&lt;/code&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Resolve the build assets&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;code&gt;dotnet restore&lt;/code&gt;
A required step in .NET Core 1.x, this step is not required starting with .NET Core 2.0.

Starting with .NET Core 2.0, &lt;code&gt;dotnet restore&lt;/code&gt; executes automatically when a new project is created. It is also run implicitly as part of &lt;code&gt;dotnet build&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;dotnet run&lt;/code&gt;.

&lt;strong&gt;Adding support for Debugging in VSCode&lt;/strong&gt;
If you are lucky, Visual Studio Code will prompt you with the following message: &quot;Required assets to build and debug are missing from 'c-sharp-quickstart'. Add them?&quot;. Click &quot;Yes&quot;.

What this does, is that it creates two files (&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/darrensimsg/c-sharp-quickstart/blob/master/.vscode/tasks.json&quot;&gt;tasks.json&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/darrensimsg/c-sharp-quickstart/blob/master/.vscode/launch.json&quot;&gt;launch.json&lt;/a&gt;) in the &lt;code&gt;.vscode&lt;/code&gt; folder. More information on what these two files does, can be found on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/OmniSharp/omnisharp-vscode/blob/master/debugger-launchjson.md&quot;&gt;Omnisharp help page&lt;/a&gt;.

&lt;strong&gt;Add Unit Testing Frameworks&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;code&gt;dotnet add package xunit``dotnet add package moq&lt;/code&gt;

Doing so will add packages references the latest versions of xUnit and Moq to your &lt;code&gt;.csproj&lt;/code&gt; files; represented by the following configurations.

[code language=&quot;plain&quot;]
[/code]

In order for xUnit to be used conveniently, an additional line of configuration needs to be added to the &lt;code&gt;.csproj&lt;/code&gt; file as follows:

[code language=&quot;plain&quot;]
```What we just did was to add a new .NET CLI Tool reference to dotnet-xunit, allowing us to execute the following command in the terminal.

[/code]

dotnet restore
dotnet xunit

[code language=&quot;plain&quot;]

_NOTE: At the time of writing, nUnit does not support .NET Core out of the box._

### Github Repository

For my convenience, I have maintained a _**quick-start C# project**_ on Github, that allows me to get started right away simply by forking the repository. This is accessible via [https://github.com/darrensimsg/c-sharp-quickstart/](https://github.com/darrensimsg/c-sharp-quickstart/).

### Useful Keyboard Shortcuts

As a developer, I found keyboard shortcuts to have increased my productivity significantly. I've recently started taking notes on [keyboard shortcuts](http://darrensim.io/posts/mac-keyboard-shortcuts-for-developers/) that I consider useful; on top of my notes on [useful GIT commands](http://darrensim.io/posts/notes-on-useful-git-commands/).

### Further Readings

* [https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/dotnet/core/tutorials/with-visual-studio-code](https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/dotnet/core/tutorials/with-visual-studio-code)
* [http://asp.net-hacker.rocks/2017/03/31/unit-testing-with-dotnetcore.html](http://asp.net-hacker.rocks/2017/03/31/unit-testing-with-dotnetcore.html)
[/code]</content><author><name>sal</name></author><summary type="html">I've recently been kept awake late into the wee hours; working on really interesting code challenges on Code Wars. While the problems are really fun to solve, one of the pains I found was to code on the web editor, which lacks the usual code editor features that I am comfortable with. Reluctant to load up the battery-draining Windows Virtual Machine just for this, I thought &quot;Why not let me just create a simple boiler plate project in .NET Core that supports xUnit, which I can readily work on using VSCode on my macOS?&quot; Language &amp; Frameworks What is .NET Core?</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/assets/images/posts/vs-code-moq-unit-test.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Letter Cases in Software Development</title><link href="/letter-cases-in-software-development-code-style/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Letter Cases in Software Development" /><published>2017-10-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-10-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/letter-cases-in-software-development-code-style</id><content type="html" xml:base="/letter-cases-in-software-development-code-style/">Coding style is a geek topic that developers talk a lot about during coding collaboration interactions. One of the first things that come up, is usually &quot;What case do we use&quot;? I was in such a scenario recently, and thought I dug a little deeper to explore all the options.
&lt;h3&gt;Camel Case&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Camel_case&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Camel_case&lt;/a&gt;

Practice of writing compound words or phrases such that each word or abbreviation in the middle of the phrase begins with a capital letter, with no intervening spaces or punctuation.

&lt;strong&gt;Examples&lt;/strong&gt;: johnDoe, lastConnectionDate
&lt;h3&gt;Pascal Case&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/PascalCase&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/PascalCase&lt;/a&gt;

Practice of writing compound words or phrases such that the first letter of each concatenated word is capitalized.

&lt;strong&gt;Examples&lt;/strong&gt;: JohnDoe, LastConnectionDate
&lt;h3&gt;Snake Case&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Snake_case&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Snake_case&lt;/a&gt;

Practice of writing compound words or phrases in which the elements are separated with one underscore character (_) and no spaces.

&lt;strong&gt;Examples&lt;/strong&gt;: john_doe, last_connection_date
&lt;h3&gt;Kebab Case&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Letter_case#Special_case_styles&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Letter_case#Special_case_styles&lt;/a&gt;

Practice of writing compound words or phrases in which the elements are separated with one dash character (-) and no spaces.

&lt;strong&gt;Examples&lt;/strong&gt;: John-doe, Last-connection-date
&lt;h3&gt;Train Case&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Letter_case#Special_case_styles&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Letter_case#Special_case_styles&lt;/a&gt;

Practice of writing compound words or phrases in which the elements are separated with one dash character (-), no spaces and every word capitalized.

&lt;strong&gt;Examples&lt;/strong&gt;: John-Doe, Last-Connection-Date</content><author><name>sal</name></author><summary type="html">Coding style is a geek topic that developers talk a lot about during coding collaboration interactions. One of the first things that come up, is usually &quot;What case do we use&quot;? I was in such a scenario recently, and thought I dug a little deeper to explore all the options. Camel Case https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Camel_case</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/assets/images/posts/text-cases.jpg" /></entry></feed>